I'm going to talk to you
about the worst types of bread
that you want to avoid eating,
as well as some alternatives
for when you're
in the supermarket,
when you want to make
something at home.
Now, bread is taking a bit
of a beating
over the last few years.
It spikes your sugar.
It could potentially cause
weight gain.
But is it breads for
or is it the type of bread?
In a word,
the type of bread
that you want to avoid
are supermarket breads.
These are mass
produced on an industrial scale
with extensive automation.
And one study
that we looked
at compared industrial,
artisanal and homemade breads.
And they found that
artisanal bread
had a lot more sugar
and markers of something
called a milliard reaction
that we'll talk
about in a second.
And that makes it
not as good for you.
In fact,
something that
I think you should avoid.
So this is your typical
supermarket bread here.
Let me tell you a bit
about supermarket bread.
So there is a high
degree of processing.
So this is a processed food.
It's more likely to contain
additives and flavourings
mainly texture.
It's including emulsifiers
hydrocolloid, preservatives.
It's going to be
it's going to have a lot more
things like vegetable oils
and as well
that shouldn't be anywhere near
a bread like sunflower
or rapeseed.
They contain
higher amounts of sugar content
because of the use of certain
ingredients, notably
soybean flour,
which contains more sugar
than wheat flour.
And then you also have
more markers of something
called the Marriott reactions.
In the Marriott reaction
is a chemical reaction
between proteins,
your amino acids,
and reducing sugars
to create melanin.
And these are the compounds
that give a distinctive
aroma of flavour.
It's very delicious,
but it could
potentially increase
the number of carcinogens
that you find in bread as well,
with potential consequences
to health.
So this is your
typical supermarket bread here.
they all pretty much
look the same.
They're all wrapped in plastic.
You can almost tell
the difference
between the bread
just by like weighing it
in your hands.
It feels very soft and spongy.
There isn't really
much substance to them,
unfortunately.
And,
if you look at the ingredients
and often like,
you know,
they've got
these green things saying
high in fibre,
rich in whole grains,
just ignore that.
Just just go straight
to the ingredients list.
That is where they cannot lie.
ingredients.
Whole, whole
mill, wheat flour,
water, yeast,
vegetable oils,
rapeseed and sustainable
palm palms.
Not sustainable salt,
wheat gluten,
emulsifiers E481471472E
soya flour.
Like I just mentioned up
the top here, like
these will have more sugars
in the flour in the bread
because of the inclusion
of soybean flour
preservative
calcium propionate,
flour treatment
agent, ascorbic acid.
A lot of ingredients
that should not be in bread.
Bread
should just be
a couple of ingredients,
some flour, water, but a salt
but a mixing.
That's all it requires.
But because supermarkets
have a job to create very cheap
and very accessible foods,
this is what we are left with.
And I'm not saying
that you should never,
ever, ever
have one of these, ever again
if you want, like a sarnie
and you know,
you want to put your favourite
ploughman's ingredients
in, fine,
you know, as a luxury item.
But I feel a lot of
people are using
this as a daily,
you know,
something to spread some,
some butter and jam
on every single day.
This is just pure sugar.
Unfortunately, I'd love to say
that this is as cheap
and accessible
and it's actually got
some health benefits.
This really does not
this is not a daily staple
in my opinion.
So that's supermarket bread.
This is the kind of stuff
that you want to avoid.
Artisanal bread
generally follows
I say generally
traditional aspects
of the homemade production
techniques at high volumes,
but without the mass production
that is found
in industrial settings.
So these are typically
more representative
of the homemade
bread, less processed,
process.
They don't contain additives
or flavourings,
but artisanal bread
can still be heavily processed
and made with
poor quality ingredients,
like an artisanal loaf produced
with 100% refined white roll.
A milled flour
will still be considered
more processed,
even if it's a sour dough.
So this is an example
of artisanal bread.
Rather than
it being white bread,
this is actually
a better quality,
artisanal bread
because it's
not just about the fact
that it's artisanal.
It's what they're
putting into the bread itself.
So this is a raw it's
very, very different
in terms of,
the texture, the weight of it.
It feels like a brick.
It has a very, very dense.
I mean, you can do this with
I'm literally
punching holes in it
if I, if I do that like this.
This is rock solid.
This is going to
have tons of fibre
and it's just got a mixture
of different grains.
You can tell
the structural
intensity of this
is so, so much better.
And the rye flour
doesn't have those nutrients
stripped from,
the grain itself,
which is where you have
all the b-vitamins, you've got
all these
different types of fibres
that is going to be
microbe supporting,
not microbe depleting.
So this is an example
of a good artisanal bread,
but it does rely on a spectrum.
So it really depends on what
your bakery or artisanal bakery
is actually
putting into the bread.
And they should be pretty
transparent about that
as well as the,
lack thereof of additives.
And the study
that we looked at,
where they compare
compared to homemade
artisanal supermarket breads,
the artisanal breads
were classified
as Nova three,
with the exception
of a particular artisanal bread
that was classified
as Nova four
because it contained
an additive and ingredient
such as powdered egg yolk.
So just
because you're artisanal,
you don't get a free pass.
Homemade breads,
on the other hand,
employ different
cooking methods.
Generally steaming,
baking, and toasting.
This can impact bread quality
and the formation
of the volatile compounds
that are found
in the Malay art.
Reaction
and one study
found that the products
of the milliard
reactions were less abundant
in homemade bread
compared to industrial
bread over here, possibly due
to lower baking temperatures.
So one of the things that
I think
we kind of miss out
on is the fact
that the I'm going to use this
as an example
of a homemade bread,
that even though it's not
technically a homemade bread,
homemade bread
is going to be used,
going to be prepared
in your own oven.
You're going to
have complete control
of any additives.
the type of flour
that you're using
and the temperature.
This is going to be really,
really rapid.
There's going to be
a much quicker fermentation,
if any.
And they're going to use quick
acting yeast as well
to get it to rise.
So this is quite unnatural
in in a word.
Whereas
this is a lot more natural
in terms of the process
used to create
good quality bread.
question I always get
is, is sour dough bread
better now?
Sour dough is a dough fermented
with lactic acid bacteria
in addition to yeasts.
And it's called a starter
Lactobacillus brevis
or Lactobacillus plantarum
or baker's yeast.
The fermentation process
adds many potential benefits,
the first of which is
nutrient absorption,
so it can improve
the inaccessibility
of certain nutrients
that you find in the grain,
so your body can
actually absorb
these nutrients
more efficiently
when consuming
sort of bread compared
to bread only made with yeast.
So they're in Lys,
you know, a very
a big difference
if you're getting true
sour dough bread.
There is also the suggestion
that it improves
gut health
and digestion as well.
So pseudo
fermentation has been shown
to reduce
something called Fodmap levels.
These are fermentable
oligo disaccharides.
People have problems to them
with them to various degrees.
If you're
on a specific IBS diet,
it would be tough to remove
FODMAPs from your diet,
and they're generally found
in quite healthy ingredients.
So garlic,
brassica
vegetables, chicory, artichoke.
You find those
also in wheat bread.
But the same process
can potentially alleviate
these gastrointestinal symptoms
and sense to people.
So sudo might have
some benefits there.
But there is a big caveat.
The evidence is still
very conflicted.
And many studies
do not show
the benefits of pseudo bread
compared to regular bread.
Bread.
Now, I don't know
whether this is
because they are not using true
sourdough bread,
because there is a lack
of established
and internationally recognised
definitions of what
a salad bread even is, i.e.
the way it's made
using microbes
and fermentation processes
and the types of flour.
It can vary
hugely
and potentially influence
the nutritional properties
of the bread itself.
So that might be why
there is conflicting evidence
as to
whether we know
is if sort of true
soda bread is at that healthy.
And so today,
the beneficial effects
of soda bread
compared to other types of
bread are not clear.
Adding more confusion
to this mix
are the supermarkets
who are marketing
certain types of bread,
a sour dough, bread.
Because there isn't
a clear definition
of what sourdough
bread actually means,
they can get away with it.
So if you're finding pseudo
bread in your supermarket,
I'd just be a little bit
hesitant.
And actually, again,
read the ingredients,
see whether it is
true sourdough bread.
It shouldn't have
additives in it.
It shouldn't have any sort of
suggestion of,
you know, sustainable palm oil,
soybean flour,
none of this stuff.
It shouldn't be in there.
so just be really, really
careful of where
you're getting
your sort of bread
from as well.
If you go to invest in bread,
which is what
I suggest people do,
go to a proper baker,
ask them about their process.
It should take days.
It shouldn't be done,
you know, mass produced
using these kind of techniques
that they're doing.
The supermarkets.
Some sections of supermarkets
have the bakery section
and you have like,
a lovely sort of wooden stand
and the smell of that,
like the air directions.
There's wonderful
distinctive aromas
in the flavours.
And they place them
on those wooden shelves
and you have, like,
this lovely
array of, like, different
whole mills and rice
and all that kind of stuff.
That's not a real bakery.
That is a fake bakery
that is essentially giving you
the impression
that you're getting a really,
really good quality bread
when you're not.
They are
employing the same mass
produce techniques in the back
and producing the,
the breads at the front.
And that is not the type
of bread that you want.
So anything
you find in the supermarket,
whether or not it's
wrapped in plastic
or whether it's something
that they're producing
in their bakery, I would
I would really,
really be cautious about
because it's not a true bakery.
You're not going to get
the benefits of whole artisanal
or homemade bread
that you can find
with far cheaper ingredients,
with far better processes.
Another question
you'll be asking yourself
is, are there any
health benefits
of having birds in your diet
at all?
Quality whole grain bread,
I think,
can be part of a healthy diet
for most people.
The reason
why is because it contains
fibre and nutrients.
It definitely provides fibre
and there are nutrients
like folate, iron,
calcium,
magnesium depending again
on the type of flour
that is been used.
And when you're thinking
about the perspective
of your diet
from what's
processed and unprocessed,
it is much better
than other
refined carbohydrates.
So it's a good swap for things
like white rice,
definitely white bread
wraps, buns, rolls,
English muffins,
certain cereals.
So obviously pastries
you want to be
moving up from that spectrum
of highly refined white
to less refined
wholemeal breads
to whole starchy vegetables
or things
like lentils legumes
that are minimally,
minimally processed
so it can be part
of a healthy diet.
but you have to be
quite specific
about the types of breads
that you're consuming.
One of the other things
I think that bread
gets compared to, wraps.
So wraps,
you know, things that you wrap
your chicken
and lettuce in and stuff
really convenient
for lunches
and sandwiches on the go.
Wraps can be very,
very processed as well.
So again,
look at the ingredients.
You'll see
lots of different sunflower
oils and vegetable oils.
You'll see
lots of preservatives.
You see tons of things
like calcium and emulsify.
It is a hyper
processed product.
So you want to make sure
that these are not part
of your daily staples.
And they
include the grab
and go sandwiches
that you're
getting from
grab and go take out,
you know, convenient cafes,
the big franchises
that are all over the UK
and the US.
Those franchises,
making their margins
by using this type of bread,
which is a
ultra processed product.
Just a quick one.
If you're enjoying
this kind of content,
you will love a free
newsletter called eat,
listen, read.
Every week
I send you a recipe
that you will absolutely love.
Something to listen to,
something to read,
sometimes something to watch.
Less than three minutes
and it will help
you have a healthier,
happier week.
You can find that
in the link down below.
So whilst I believe
that bread can be
part of a healthy diet,
it really depends
on the quality of your bread
as well.
The quality of
your carbohydrates
actually matter.
There was a study
published in Jama
that found that substituting
refined grains,
starchy vegetables
and sugary beverages
with equal amounts
of whole grains, fruits,
and non-starchy vegetables
was tied
to a decrease in weight
over the four year
study period.
So this sort of simplistic idea
that bread is going
to make you gain weight
and you shouldn't
have any carbs in your diet,
I think is overly simplistic.
It really depends
on the quality of your bread,
the quality
of your carbohydrates,
not the fact that bread
will make you lose weight.
bread will make you
gain weight,
or bread
is going to spike
your sugar levels.
It really depends
on the quality of the bread
as well as what
you eat it with as well.
So don't forget that.
I mean, I don't know
many people that will just eat
this toasted on its own.
You usually would have this
with a bit of fat,
whether it's 100%
peanut butter, or you can have,
some salad leaves on it,
some extra virgin olive oil,
some cheese,
some other sources of protein,
like with the rich slim fish
or mackerel
or something like that.
You're going to have this
as part of the food matrix.
And so even though this
has got some degree
of processing in it,
it's going to be a lot better,
than the other types
of refined carbohydrates
that you could potentially pair
this with, like a bagel
or a wrap, for example.
So in terms of alternatives
to supermarket bread,
making your own,
we've actually got,
a recipe on our app,
soaked oats bread.
You find this on the Doctor's
Kitchen, app?
You'll be able to find that,
just download it
using the link down below.
This recipe actually has
pumpkin seeds.
Sunflower seeds,
white
sesame seeds,
porridge, whole oats
that are raw
chia, flax
seed, buckwheat
flour, bit of salt,
bit of olive oil,
bit of, bicarb.
And that's it.
Like that,
all the ingredients
you can read,
they're all super healthy.
They are incredibly diverse.
They're wonderful
for your gut health.
This is the kind of bread
that you want to be consuming.
And now there are
some breads out there
that are providing a similar,
sort of,
version of homemade breads
that you can make
that's actually
a gluten free version.
This is a brand
that you can find
in supermarket.
It's but not made
by the supermarkets themselves.
This is called Seed Fall.
And they have a great,
list of ingredients,
on the front of the
packaging as well,
which I think is always like
a bit of a telltale sign
that they're proud
they're not trying
to hide anything.
And again,
this has got oats,
sunflower seeds,
linseed, golden
linseed, pumpkin seeds, chia,
psyllium husk, organic
apple cider vinegar,
bit of salt. That's it.
And this can be found
in some supermarkets.
And again
if you feel it it's firm.
It looks like proper bread.
It's similar in weight
and texture to this.
So you can tell
just from looking at how
non spongy it is.
And like there's no structure
to that whatsoever.
This is a good product.
The only issue with these
is that they're a lot
more expensive.
This is four slices for £3.
Whereas you can make out
in the doctor's
kitchen up for less
than a cup of coffee
for subscription for a month.
And there's a free trial as I.
If you want a checklist
for the healthiest
breads to go and eat,
I can't go through
every single brand,
so I'm going to give you
the sort of cheat sheet
to how you can choose
healthier bread.
So the first thing is
you want 100% whole grains
as the first ingredient,
like whole wheat or oats
or barley or rye.
So first thing,
you want to be looking for
minimal ingredients.
Quality bread
should be for main ingredients.
The grain,
yeast, water, salt or pseudo
starter as well.
Maybe some seeds,
maybe some extra virgin
olive oil.
Nothing else.
No more sapphires?
No preservatives,
no need for
any added, minerals
like calcium. None of that.
You want it to be high fibre.
So over
six grams
per 100g of product
is how much fibre you want.
The kind of breads
that we create
in the doctor's
kitchen, on the doctor's
kitchen up
are upwards of ten grams.
And we also have 8
to 9g of protein
as well in our breads.
But it's quite hard to get
that in your regular bread
or even your artisanal
bread or,
baker's bread as well.
And,
I think some bonus things
that you'd want
in a good quality bread,
or supercharged
bread, more
so things like flax seed
because they add fibre
and healthy fats.
you also want a stone
milled flour,
a sour dough, sprouted grains.
These all add extra nutrients
that are absorbable
for you as well.
local grains,
if you wanted to support
locally
and unbleached flour as well.
I tend to go for organic
where possible,
because I think
organic is our sort of vote
toward
a more sustainable
and cleaner landscape.
But I don't think it's possible
for everyone to go organic.
just depending
on where you are
in the country as well.
And the red flags,
I've already sort of,
hit this, home,
I think quite a bit.
Emulsifiers, particularly
things like CMC,
also known as carboxyl
methyl cellulose.
It's commonly used
in industrial
bread to add volume
and shelf life
and to gluten free
baking to add volume,
much like gluten proteins do.
It's linked
to detrimental impact
on the gut microbiota
and symptoms
of the gist of comfort.
So if you see
emulsifiers like CMC carboxyl,
methyl cellulose,
please avoid those
and any preservatives,
flavourings, added sugar.
the other additives
that I just talked about
as well as soya flour
because of the sugar issues,
please avoid those,
as much as possible.
I hope this has been helpful.
If I've missed any,
issues with breads
that you think
I should have, approach
or I should have, discussed
and let me know
and, let me know,
what your favourite breads
are as well. In the comments.
I want to know.
I want to know if I've missed
any of the ones
that I should be
looking out for.
If you love that episode,
you'll love this one
where I do a deep dive
into the health benefits
and the health disadvantages
of certain types of oats.
You can check that out
right here.